<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Text of "To the Lighthouse"</title>
        <author xml:id="Woolf" sameAs="https://dbpedia.org/page/Virginia_Woolf">Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Peize Yu</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="hogarth_press" ref="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hogarth_Press">Hogarth Press</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Publicly available from woolfonline.com</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title xml:id="To_the_Lighthouse">To the Lighthouse</title>
          <author ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</author>
          <date when="1927">1927</date>
        </bibl>
        <ref target="https://dbpedia.org/page/To_the_Lighthouse http://www.woolfonline.com"/>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>TEI encoding of excerpt from Virginia Woolf's printed edition of "To the Lighthouse"</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="chapter" n="1">
        <head>I</head>
        <p>
            "Yes, of course, if it's fine to-morrow," said Mrs.<lb/>
            Ramsay. "But you'll have to be up with the<lb/>
            lark," she added.<lb/>
        </p>
        <p>
            To her son these words conveyed an extra-<lb/>
            ordinary joy, as if it were settled the expedition<lb/>
            were bound to take place, and the wonder to<lb/>
            which he had looked forward, for years and years<lb/>
            it seemed, was, after a night's darkness and a day's<lb/>
            sail, within touch. Since he belonged, even at<lb/>
            the age of six, to that great clan which cannot<lb/>
            keep this feeling separate from that, but must let<lb/>
            future prospects, with their joys and sorrows,<lb/>
            cloud what is actually at hand, since to such people<lb/>
            even in earliest childhood any turn in the wheel<lb/>
            of sensation has the power to crystallise and<lb/>
            transfix the moment upon which its gloom or<lb/>
            radiance rests, James Ramsay, sitting on the floor<lb/>
            cutting out pictures from the illustrated catalogue<lb/>
            of the Army and Navy Stores, endowed the<lb/>
            picture of a refrigerator as his mother spoke with<lb/>
            heavenly bliss. It was fringed with joy. The<lb/>
            <pb n="11"/>
            wheelbarrow, the lawn-mower, the sound of poplar<lb/>
            trees, leaves whitening before rain, rooks cawing,<lb/>
            brooms knocking, dresses rustling—all these<lb/>
            were so coloured and distinguished in his mind<lb/>
            that he had already his private code, his secret<lb/>
            language, though he appeared the image of stark<lb/>
            and uncompromising severity, with his high fore-<lb/>
            head and his fierce blue eyes, impeccably candid<lb/>
            and pure, frowning slightly at the sight of human<lb/>
            frailty, so that his mother, watching him guide<lb/>
            his scissors neatly round the refrigerator, imagined<lb/>
            him all red and ermine on the Bench or directing<lb/>
            a stern and momentous enterprise in some crisis<lb/>
            of public affairs.<lb/>
        </p>
        <p>
            "But," said his father, stopping in front of<lb/>
            the drawing-room window, "it won’t be fine."<lb/>
            Had there been an axe handy, a poker, or any<lb/>
            weapon that would have gashed a hole in his<lb/>
            father’s breast and killed him, there and then,<lb/>
            James would have seized it. Such were the<lb/>
            extremes of emotion that Mr. Ramsay excited<lb/>
            in his children’s breasts by his mere presence;<lb/>
            standing, as now, lean as a knife, narrow as the<lb/>
            blade of one, grinning sarcastically, not only with<lb/>
            the pleasure of disillusioning his son and casting<lb/>
            ridicule upon his wife, who was ten thousand<lb/>
            times better in every way than he was (James<lb/>
            thought), but also with some secret conceit at his<lb/>
            <pb n="12"/>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>