<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Diary of Virginia Woolf</title>
        <author xml:id="Woolf" sameAs="https://dbpedia.org/page/Virginia_Woolf">Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Peize Yu</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher xml:id="NYPL" sameAs="https://www.nypl.org/">The New York Public Library</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Publicly available from The New York Public Library's Digital Collections</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title xml:id="1928 Diary">1928 Diary</title>
          <author ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</author>
          <date when="1928">1928</date>
        </bibl>
        <ref target="https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/6c46d770-bc67-013b-8012-0242ac110002"/>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>TEI encoding of excerpt from Virginia Woolf's 1928 Diary, with both the manuscript and the text.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <facsimile>
    <head>Manuscript of <persName xml:id="Woolf">Virginia Woolf</persName>'s diary in 1928</head>
    <graphic url="Diaries-1928.jpg"/>
      <ptr target="https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/6c46d770-bc67-013b-8012-0242ac110002"/>
  </facsimile>

  <text>
    <body>
      <p>
        at three in the night. He came in - a fresh tall<lb/>
        old man (such was my impression) with a very<lb/>
        determined look about his face. I said how nice it<lb/>
        was to Sheffield; has a thick moustache; a<lb/>
        red beard that came down, very trim. But when he saw<lb/>
        perfectly trim very large. They then - he<lb/>
        was becomes growing in mercy when the letter -<lb/>
        how I wish discovered I discovered in the "Times"<lb/>
        brushed, neat, urbane. They came through dinner<lb/>
        he turned to me&amp;the talk remembering<lb/>
        platform. Charming story teller; he told me Fitzgerald<lb/>
        had in mind an article on Goldsmith I opened -<lb/> 
        Burnt me away when Lyttelton appeared. I got<lb/>
        these from his yarn manner. J. M.B. does himself so<lb/>
        whether you encouraged me more day so<lb/>
        telling has me he is unrivaled. "In a minute now<lb/>
        he came in the is constabulary." Like a general<lb/>
        he said, intent directly. What a strange power. A<lb/>
        which is hard flaxen. Just always closes. At<lb/>
        Charming now, he said "very kind expression, -<lb/> 
        What had Coleridge really published in - equal<lb/>
        to W - at that time? Between Waverley days -<lb/>
        To W - think - now she you wrote. I do an<lb/>
        I was one of his colleagues. Yellow in the way<lb/>
        looking. But not quite purple too slightly<lb/>
        he asked me what I wrote - to black green. He<lb/>
        took me in his. Therefore when a literary. I went to<lb/>
        buy it &amp; wrote him that I much you would deem<lb/>
        but not great charms -<lb/>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>

