<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Diary of Virginia Woolf (1928)</title>
        <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Peize Yu</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>The New York Public Library Digital Collections</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Publicly available from The New York Public Library's Digital Collections</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title>From the Diaries of Virginia Woolf</title>
          <author>Virginia Woolf</author>
          <date when="1928">1928</date>
        </bibl>
        <ref target="https://digitalcollections.nypl.org/items/510d47dd-e5d3-a3d9-e040-e00a18064a99"/>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>TEI encoding of excerpt from Virginia Woolf’s 1928 diary with both text and manuscript image.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="diary" xml:id="vw-diary-1928">
        <head>From the Diaries of Virginia Woolf</head>

        <p>
          at three in the night. He came in - a fresh tall old man (such was my impression)
          with a very determined look about his face. I said how nice it was to Sheffield;
          has a thick moustache; a red beard that came down, very trim. But when he saw
          perfectly trim very large. They then - he was becomes growing in mercy when
          the letter - how I wish discovered I discovered in the "Times" brushed, neat,
          urbane. They came through dinner he turned to me &amp; the talk remembering
          platform. Charming story teller; he told me Fitzgerald had in mind an article
          on Goldsmith I opened - Burnt me away when Lyttelton appeared. I got these
          from his yarn manner. J. M.B. does himself so whether you encouraged me more
          day so telling has me he is unrivaled. "In a minute now he came in the is
          constabulary." Like a general he said, intent directly. What a strange power.
          A which is hard flaxen. Just always closes. At Charming now, he said "very
          kind expression, - What had Coleridge really published in - equal to W - at
          that time? Between Waverley days - To W - think - now she you wrote. I do an
          I was one of his colleagues. Yellow in the way looking. But not quite purple
          too slightly he asked me what I wrote - to black green. He took me in his.
          Therefore when a literary. I went to buy it &amp; wrote him that I much you
          would deem but not great charms -
        </p>

        <figure>
          <head>Manuscript of Virginia Woolf's diary in 1928</head>
          <graphic url="Diaries-1928.jpg"/>
          <figDesc>Facsimile of the 1928 diary manuscript page by Virginia Woolf.</figDesc>
        </figure>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
