<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>From the Diary of Virginia Woolf</title>
        <composer xml:id="Argento" ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dominick_Argento">Dominick Argento</composer>
        <author xml:id="Woolf" sameAs="https://dbpedia.org/page/Virginia_Woolf">Virginia Woolf</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoded by</resp>
          <persName>Peize Yu</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Boosey &amp; Hawkes</publisher>
        <date when="1975">1975</date>
        <availability>
          <p>This encoding is for scholarly analysis only.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <title xml:id="From_the_Diary_of_Virginia_Woolf">From the Diary of Virginia Woolf</title>
          <composer ref="#Argento">Dominick Argento</composer>
          <date when="1974">1974</date>
        </bibl>
        <ref target="https://www.lieder.net/lieder/assemble_texts.html?SongCycleId=2366"/>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>TEI encoding of Argento's song cycle based on excerpts from Virginia Woolf's diaries.</p>
      </projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <creation>
        <date when="1974">1974</date>
      </creation>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords>
          <term>Song cycle</term>
          <term>Diary excerpts</term>
          <term>Modernism</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <figure>
        <head>The Writer's Desk</head>
        <graphic url="Woolf's Desk.jpg"/>
        <figDesc>
            The desk of Virginia Woolf.
          <ptr target="https://exhibits.library.duke.edu/exhibits/show/baskin2016/woolf"/>
        </figDesc>
      </figure>
      <div type="song" xml:id="song1">
        <head>The Diary (April, 1919)</head>
        <p>
          What sort of diary should I like mine to be? Something . . . so<lb/>
          elastic that it will embrace anything, solemn, slight or beautiful<lb/>
          that comes into my mind. I should like it to resemble some deep<lb/>
          old desk . . . in which one flings a mass of odds and ends<lb/>
          without looking them through. I should like to come back, after<lb/>
          a year or two, and find that the collection had sorted itself<lb/>
          and refined itself and coalesced, as such deposits so mysteriously<lb/>
          do, into a mould, transparent enough to reflect the light of our life.
        </p>
        <note>Text by <persName ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</persName>, April 1919.</note>
      </div>

      <div type="song" xml:id="song2">
        <head>Anxiety (October, 1920)</head>
        <p>
          Why is life so tragic; so like a little strip of pavement over an abyss.<lb/>
          I look down; I feel giddy; I wonder how I am ever to walk to the end.<lb/>
          But why do I feel this: Now that I say it I don't feel it. The fire<lb/>
          burns; we are going to hear The Beggar's Opera. Only it lies all<lb/>
          about me; I can't keep my eyes shut . . . And with it all how happy<lb/>
          I am – if it weren't for my feeling that it's a strip of pavement<lb/>
          over an abyss.
        </p>
        <note>Text by <persName ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</persName>, October 1920.</note>
      </div>

      <div type="song" xml:id="song3">
        <head>Fancy (February, 1927)</head>
        <p>
          Why not invent a new kind of play; as for instance:<lb/>
          Woman thinks:<lb/>
          He does.<lb/>
          Organ plays.<lb/>
          She writes.<lb/>
          They say:<lb/>
          She sings.<lb/>
          Night speaks.<lb/>
          They miss.
        </p>
        <note>Text by <persName ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</persName>, February 1927.</note>
      </div>

      <div type="song" xml:id="song4">
        <head>Hardy's Funeral (January, 1928)</head>
        <p>
          Yesterday we went to Hardy's funeral. What did I think of? Of Max<lb/>
          Beerbohm's letter . . . or a lecture . . . about women's writing.<lb/>
          At intervals some emotion broke in. But I doubt the capacity of<lb/>
          the human animal for being dignified in ceremony. One catches a<lb/>
          bishop's frown and twitch; sees his polished shiny nose; suspects<lb/>
          the rapt spectacled young priest, gazing at the cross he carries,<lb/>
          of being a humbug . . . next here is the coffin, an overgrown one;<lb/>
          like a stage coffin, covered with a white satin cloth; bearers<lb/>
          elderly gentlemen rather red and stiff, holding to the corners;<lb/>
          pigeons flying outside . . . processions to poets corner;<lb/>
          dramatic "In sure and certain hope of immortality" perhaps<lb/>
          melodramatic . . . Over all this broods for me some uneasy sense<lb/>
          of change and mortality and how partings are deaths; and then a<lb/>
          sense of my own fame . . . and a sense of the futility of it all.
        </p>
        <note>Text by <persName ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</persName>, January 1928.</note>
      </div>

      <div type="song" xml:id="song5">
        <head>Rome (May, 1935)</head>
        <p>
          Rome: tea. Tea in café. Ladies in bright coats and white hats.<lb/>
          Music. Look out and see people like movies . . . Ices.<lb/>
          Old man who haunts the Greco . . . Fierce large jowled old<lb/>
          ladies . . . talking about Monaco. Talleyrand. Some very<lb/>
          poor black wispy women. The effect of dowdiness produced<lb/>
          by wispy hair. Sunday café . . . Very cold. The prime Minister's<lb/>
          letter offering to recommend me for the Companion of Honour. No.
        </p>
        <note>Text by <persName ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</persName>, May 1935.</note>
      </div>

      <div type="song" xml:id="song6">
        <head>War (June, 1940)</head>
        <p>
          This, I thought yesterday, may be my last walk . . . the war –<lb/>
          our waiting while the knives sharpen for the operation – has<lb/>
          taken away the outer wall of security. No echo comes back. I<lb/>
          have no surroundings . . . Those familiar circumlocutions –<lb/>
          those standards – which have for so many years given back an<lb/>
          echo and so thickened my identity are all wide and wild as<lb/>
          the desert now. I mean, there is no "autumn," no winter.<lb/>
          We pour to the edge of a precipice . . . and then? I can't<lb/>
          conceive that there will be a 27th June 1941.
        </p>
        <note>Text by <persName ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</persName>, June 1940.</note>
      </div>

      <div type="song" xml:id="song7">
        <head>Parents (December, 1940)</head>
        <p>
          How beautiful they were, those old people – I mean father and<lb/>
          mother – how simple, how clear, how untroubled. I have been<lb/>
          dipping into old letters and father's memoirs. He loved her:<lb/>
          oh and was so candid and reasonable and transparent . . .<lb/>
          How serene and gay even, their life reads to me: no mud;<lb/>
          no whirlpools. And so human – with the children and the<lb/>
          little hum and song of the nursery. But if I read as a<lb/>
          contemporary I shall lose my child's vision and so must<lb/>
          stop. Nothing turbulent; nothing involved; no introspection.
        </p>
        <note>Text by <persName ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</persName>, December 1940.</note>
      </div>

      <div type="song" xml:id="song8">
        <head>Last Entry (March, 1941)</head>
        <p>
          No: I intend no introspection. I mark Henry James' sentence:<lb/>
          Observe perpetually. Observe the oncome of age. Observe greed.<lb/>
          Observe my own despondency. By that means it becomes<lb/>
          serviceable. Or so I hope. I insist upon spending this<lb/>
          time to the best advantage. I will go down with my colours<lb/>
          flying . . . Occupation is essential. And now with some pleasure<lb/>
          I find that it's seven; and must cook dinner. Haddock and<lb/>
          sausage meat. I think it is true that one gains a certain<lb/>
          hold on sausage and haddock by writing them down.
        </p>
        <note>Text by <persName ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</persName>, March 1941.</note>
      </div>

      <listPerson>
        <person>
          <persName ref="#Argento">Dominick Argento</persName>
          <note>Composer of the song cycle</note>
        </person>
        <person>
          <persName ref="#Woolf">Virginia Woolf</persName>
          <note>Author of diary texts</note>
        </person>
      </listPerson>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
